Hello and welcome to the second AMR
overture round table discussion in
preparation of the 2026
PCA General Assembly in Louisville,
Kentucky.
Uh I'm Derek Radney. I'm a pastor at
Trinity Church in Winston-Salem, North
Carolina. And I'm the host today on
behalf of the Alliance for Mission and
Renewal.
Uh the Alliance exists to help foster a
unified, faithful, and flourishing PCA.
And just recently we published our
theological vision uh that clarifies
what we're seeking for the PCA. And part
of that document talks about our desire
to embody and cultivate in the PCA a
posture of gratitude, hope, and trust.
And so this round table really is one of
the ways that we want to try to promote
that posture in the culture of our
denomination. So the purpose of today is
really to invite godly and wise and
experienced elders to discuss the
overtures before the General Assembly
this year uh in a way that's charitable,
um sharpening, and hopefully edifying to
viewers as we prepare for uh the General
Assembly in June. So with me today uh I
have three guests. Uh the first is Dr.
David Coffin. Uh he's well known to many
of you. Uh he is a a planter and a
pastor of New Hope Presbyterian Church
in Fairfax, Virginia for over 30 years.
Um he's married for over 50 years with
three adult children.
Uh he has his PhD from Westminster
Theological Seminary in Philadelphia in
historical theology. And as you all
know, he's been engaged in the work of
our denominational courts for many
years, including uh the Standing
Judicial Commission.
I also have with us today Ruling Elder
Howie Donaho. Uh Howie was a pilot in
the Air Force for 8 years and then for
American Airlines for 35 years.
He's been married for 41 years with
three daughter daughters and two sons
and 12 grandchildren. And he's been a
member of the PCA for 44 years.
Uh he's served as a a ruling elder in
five churches, in four mission churches,
and four Presbyteries. He's now in
Boise, Idaho at Boise Presbyterian as a
ruling elder. And he was the 47th
General Assembly Moderator in Dallas,
Texas. He's been on the SJC for 28
years, served on Nominating Committee
and RPR uh many times.
And then I also have Teaching Elder
Steve Tipton, uh Dr. Steve Tipton here
with us. He is the pastor of Covenant
Presbyterian Church in Panama City,
Florida. He's been an ordained minister
in the PCA since 2010 and has his PhD in
historical theology from uh Evangelical
Theological Faculty in Leuven, Belgium.
Uh, he has served several years on the
Overtures Committee.
He's chaired the committee in 2024
and also served on RPR, CCB, and the
SJC. So, men, I want to welcome you and
thank you for doing this and taking your
time to do it. Uh, I believe this
discussion will be a help to the General
Assembly and help us all do better work
as we speak uh as we seek the Spirit's
guidance together.
So, uh just a little bit about our
format today. Um, what we're going to do
here is discuss overtures that are sent
up to the General Assembly here in uh
2026. Uh, as hopefully you know,
overtures are proposals that are sent by
Presbyteries that usually involve
proposed changes to our Book of Church
Order, but can also deal with other
matters like changes to our doctrinal
standards or changes to the Rules of um
of Assembly Operations or create study
committees or even make other
affirmations and statements.
Um, this year we're seeing a lot of
proposed changes around the RAO, the
Rules of Assembly Operation, as well as
the Book of Church Order, the BCO
uh regarding judicial process, uh the
deacon officer ordination questions that
have been raised. Uh, and in my
judgment, the flood of officer overtures
is a result of kind of an online
firestorm that that happened this year
this past winter and there's been a lot
of debate about that about what's
permissible and what's not
and so whether or not that online
discussion is reflective of the PCA
remains to be seen but it certainly has
caused a lot of proposals come to this
General Assembly.
Our goal today is to or excuse me my
goal today is really to guide us and to
try to keep us on track try to encourage
us to be efficient and I'm going to make
mainly try to moderate and keep us
moving and try not to weigh in with my
own thoughts and we want to hear from
these men.
The plan is to first discuss how to
handle all the overtures just given the
the sheer number of them and then to
kind of walk through some of the key
overtures that that these men feel are
are worth passing or are or not
especially not good or are especially
important.
So we're going to focus on the most
consequential. I've talked with all
these men beforehand to kind of get a
sense of what they think would be worth
discussing.
So with all that said let's go ahead and
and get started and actually hear from
our guests. So men in recent years
the overtures committee has averaged
around 33 overtures that they've had to
deal with this year
83 as of today or actually excuse me I
think yeah 83 as of today which is May
5th
have been sent up to the overtures
committee. 17 came from one Presbytery
and as far as I understand they were
drafted by one man but even if you
remove those this is clearly a
record-breaking number and some people
see this as a sign of health that
reflects an increased interest in our
polity others see it as a sign of
polarization and evidence that the PCA
is divided and others think it just
shows everyone has too much time on
their hands. So two questions for you
all to kind of get us started, which is
what do you think of the high number of
overtures this year?
And what does that say about the PCA?
And then how do you think the overtures
committee should go about handling that?
So I'm going to start with you David,
kind of ask you to get us started on
answering that question.
Um, I think and this is a view I've had
even before the onslaught of all these
overtures.
Um, they're very shifted in the time
that I've been coming to the General
Assembly.
Uh
overtures
to amend
the Book of Church Order
typically were a part of a constructive
program, generally for the whole church.
But over the last few years, it seems to
me at least, overtures have uh
to change the book have uh
changed into theological weapons to try
and advance a particular cause.
And [clears throat] I think that is not
a healthy thing.
I don't really uh
what I've
tried to argue is that if we have
differences in the first place, we ought
to be talking to each other.
Uh and writing to each other and so on.
And then if we can't settle the
differences, then judicial processes are
open to us need be.
Uh
but it's turned out that the first
weapon that seems to come to hand is to
want to change the book to settle the
questions that are dividing us and that
seems to me a profound mistake.
How do you think the overtures committee
should try to tackle the sheer number
this year? Do you think there's a a good
strategy in doing that?
Howie said some great strategies he's
been working on, but I'm not confident
there's any strategy that's going to
besides just saying outright we're not
going to deal with all these. We're
going to pick the ones we think we can
get uh done and the ones that are
important and just leave the rest.
Okay. Howie, why don't you jump in and
and tell us what you think it means that
we have so many this year and how you
think we should deal with them.
Well, as you probably know I've spilled
more ink probably with even Steven David
have over the years. Um
part of me
>> [clears throat]
>> is encouraged by people's
engagement, but I'm also very
sympathetic about what David just said.
In fact, on the um
I think there are 10 diaconal related
overtures and
in the commentary I'm drafting I suggest
that we punt them all back to the
Presbyteries
and for men to get together for meals
over the next year and hash it out.
Let somebody write the definitive paper,
circulate it, things like that. So, I'm
sympathetic to what David said about
trying to accomplish things offline
rather than
online, but we can't certainly can't
have 83 overtures
sent to the assembly for 13 and 1/2
hours of overture committee business.
If we're going to have that many every
year, you're going to have to handle
them like RPR and meet in May and take
three or four days to do it, which I
certainly don't want to do or advocate
that. So,
I don't know how to put a cap on
overtures. I don't think we can, but uh
at um
1 minute before 4:00 on Mon- on Tuesday
in Louisville, I'm going to make a
motion that we punt everything that's
remaining and and adjourn at 4:00. So,
there you go.
All right. Steve, we love to hear from
you. What do you think this means, the
high volume, and then how do you think
we should deal with them?
Yeah, well,
as I looked at the list, I think a lot
of them, and I think this is true year
after year, are
um reactions, in a sense, to either the
previous year's assembly. You know, so
there are some that are reacting to,
let's say, the the issues with M&A or
the A seed with the coordinator and
clerk, or they're reacting to
um an unprecedented number of floor
nominees during the nominating
committee.
There's reactions to the length of the
RPR report. Um there are obviously
reactions to the things that are going
on more broadly than the nominations,
such as the issue with with deacons, et
cetera. Um
and I'm not saying that all reactions
are bad, um but
you know, the longer that I looked into
this, especially, you know, whether it's
the permanent committee issues or even
the nominating committee issues, maybe
even the RPR issues, I think it it
sometimes it's a bad idea to react one
year purely on the basis of what
happened the previous year and not
realize that there's a longer
we have 51 years of of examples. I
realize that some of the systems have
changed, but of the process working more
or less as intended. And so, um a lot of
those for me, even if I have some
sympathy with some of the overtures
themselves, I still want to say
I'm not sure it's really broken. I think
these are features rather than bugs, and
it's working as intended. We should uh
we should we should at least give it one
more year before we decide we're just
going to throw everything out. Um
obviously, you know, some of them are
more important than others and and we'll
have to take them up. Um, and I think
that's the that's how you handle them. I
mean, it's just triage at the end of the
day.
Um, and
uh my hope would be, let's say there's
you you said there's 83, let's say we
get through 40, which would be
monumental. Let's say we get through 40.
Well, that means there's 43 that get
sent back.
And one of the things you are saying to
the presbyteries generally is, send as
many overtures as you want,
but if it's but if it doesn't rise up to
a level of importance, it's just not
going to get it's not going to get
looked at. It's not going to get
handled. And so it might self-correct to
a certain degree where we see we
I'm hoping we don't see 83 again next
year. Uh, but we might see um many of
those this is not that important uh etc.
So.
If I could add one word on that, um,
the the normal procedure
would be to send overtures on to the
next assembly.
And I do hope that we don't do that.
I think we just send them back.
Refer back, okay. Howie, what were you
going to say?
Yeah, Steve and I are working on and
Dave will be looped in and and others on
the overtures committee eventually be
looped in. Um,
to try to draft an order of business.
And um,
the overtures fall into distinct
categories, RAO,
diaconal, judicial, quality,
statements, and um, I saw Steven's draft
Steve's draft this morning
and it looked like um,
we were going uh
deal with the most important ones in
those categories as like the varsity and
then may or may not get to the second
round of the junior varsity overtures in
each of those categories or something
like that, but we need to
um figure out a way to triage them and
not
not do them randomly because that that
confuses my brain. Um
at least
you know, the three three to five most
important in each category and deal with
those, and then see where we're at at
the end of that.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's always incredibly helpful
that um some of y'all do that work ahead
of time to try to set the committee on a
good direction about how to go through
everything. Especially when you can work
>> Yeah, I think that's going to be
uploaded to the
overtures committee share file
a couple weeks before the GA for people
to look at, so it's not just day of.
All right, well, let's let's go on to
the next question, which is just very
briefly, what are the one or two
overtures that you would like to see
pass?
And then if you want to mention
one or two overtures you really don't
want to pass. Uh and we don't have to
talk much about the substance, but you
can just say, this overture on this
issue, thumbs up. This overture on this
issue, thumbs down. So, I'll go in the
same order. David, do you want to tell
us what you would like to see pass and
what you don't want to see pass?
I I was thrilled to see overture seven
be submitted. That's [snorts] um
changing the RAO concerning how RPR um
reports.
And I think it's a
uh brilliant idea.
I don't think there's any reason why
when RPR is making a recommendation, it
can't go directly to the Presbytery
first, and it doesn't need to be voted
on
by the assembly.
Then when it comes back to RPR, at that
point RPR proposes, do we need to have
the assembly say, we're going to either
uh accept it or send it to the SJC for a
case.
I think that would uh be a wonderful way
to streamline the business and still
enable RPR to do the
extraordinarily important work that
they're doing. I think otherwise
uh
the chance that any commissioner has
written read that whole report is very
slim.
Okay, we'll come back to
discussion about that one. Anyone's you
don't want to see pass? Well, let me
mention the second that I
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, go for it. Yeah. I'm concerned
with
and that is over 243.
Um
that I think we're in
real danger of losing losing the
possibility of getting good leadership
at the level of committees and agencies
in the state of clerk. I can't imagine
anybody who would leave their home, move
to Atlanta with a job they only may have
for 1 year.
But on top of that once you're there, I
think
to be have to be reelected every year
and especially gracious if it goes to
2/3.
Uh you won't get real leadership. You'll
get people
I don't want to be slanderous to the
House of Representatives, but many of
those men get to Washington and they
continue their campaign for the next 2
years because they know they won't be
there if they don't.
Uh
it'll weaken the possibility for bolder
leadership if the man has to fear
am I going to lose my majority or
heaven help us
2/3.
The ones I'm Are you are you want to do
them all at once? Yeah, just real quick.
What do you not want to see pass and
we'll talk about them later. Over 280 uh
it's on the critical race theory. I I
think I'm I'm myself I'm going to move
that part of that is ruled out of order
because I think it violates our rules to
have it I
I'm very unhappy with that and
overture 82
uh that is uh
the uh
whole rehashing of the act on act in act
against business from many many years
ago.
I was on the committee
that had to do with all of that.
And I I
I think this is a huge backward step. We
we haven't been
addressing these kinds of issues for
uh
30 years and I think it's it would be a
great shame for us to go backward.
Okay.
All right, Howie, what about you? What
do you want to see pass and uh what do
you not want to see pass?
Well,
in my commentary there's 20 I recommend
answering in the affirmative but I'll
focus on a couple.
I like David think uh Pacific Northwest
overture seven
on the RPR report will be a very good
addition. It's good that we have the RPR
chairman on this call so that he can
chime in and um I actually
if the overture gets amended I would
like to see
Westminster 27
uh get some discussion in the overtures
committee. I don't like it as it is. I
think the threshold is
far too low and the wording is
problematic but I think it could be
amended in such a way
uh that assumption of original
jurisdiction could become a possible
thing which right now it really isn't.
Yeah, we've taken a couple stabs at that
recently and that's not not worked out.
Well, I don't think I could sign on to
it unless it was a 20% of the presbytery
threshold but
um
I think the the one that gets my least
favorite award of the year is Northwest
Georgia 49 that wants to increase
ruling elder representation,
um which would mean a church of 40
communing members could have three
ruling elders General Assembly. Um I'm
very much not in favor of that.
Okay.
Steve, over to you. What do you want to
see pass? What do you definitely not
want to see pass?
Yeah. Well, so um we'll have to talk
about those other issues uh later on in
the call. Um I think that, you know,
some of the ones that I looked at that
were
um
you know, somewhat minor in one sense,
but I think are are helpful would be
something like eight on a discipline
level to set or sorry, this is the the
one issue with nominating committee I
thought was good that uh have a to have
an earlier deadline for floor noms. I
think that made sense.
Um I think that's Let's see.
Uh 35 is I think it's going to be an
interesting discussion about deadlines
for issuing of indictment. Um that may
be a premature reaction to something
that really has it's it's ongoing that
hasn't actually happened yet, so to
speak. So, that's one issue. Um
I I also There's There's a collection of
them. I think it includes one of the
ones that uh David said he didn't like
at all, um
but that are touching on the issue of um
churches without uh session or at least
a session that doesn't have a quorum and
and how those things uh need to operate.
Um I I don't like any of them
necessarily as they're written. I think
they need some amendments. I thought the
Rocky Mountain one
included some very interesting things
that seem to have absolutely nothing to
do with what the overture was about, and
that may be what David was referring to.
Um but having a clear established
procedure in the book that doesn't
require you to read a whole bunch of SJC
cases, I think would be helpful if we
can if we can arrive at that. Um as far
as you know, just the really bad ones
again,
um I think um
uh
I know this may be going out on a limb.
37 allowing women to serve as ordained
deacons, I think that was horrible. Uh
but that's a conversation we can uh
circle back to. Um I think the central
floor uh consent to the govern for
assistant pastors. Um I I know that
there was some discussion about this
last year.
Uh I think it is a
39. Yeah, grave misunderstanding of
authority
um and plenary principles um
and then there's probably a handful of
other ones. I think the one from
uh New York State about uh
uh shall institute charges against
somebody who says something online.
Uh
A lot of these were
Thank you. A lot of these were we we
have
there's already a a provision in one
sense for it in the book. You know, you
can always bring charges or uh do a 31-2
or whatever. So,
uh I thought the the those things were a
little little extra so to speak, but uh
that's kind of my list.
Okay.
All right, well, let's start off uh with
maybe some ones that I think there's a
lot of agreement on uh kind of some
maybe non-controversial ones.
Uh let's talk about overture four from
Pacific Northwest um about uh day of
prayer and thanks for adult professions
of faith. Um how are you going to speak
to that at all? Just very briefly.
>> Sure. Yeah. Our presbytery just thought
and we filed this one early.
Just thought it'd be nice to have one
overture that was a happy one.
Uh so
>> [laughter]
>> so we sent that in. It uh I'm assuming
it'll pass. It'll take 2 minutes of the
floor time and um it's wonderful to give
thanks to uh
for adult professions of faith, adult
baptisms, and just happy things, so.
Yeah.
Uh there's also overture 50 by
Mississippi Valley uh about a day of
fasting and prayer for revival and
renewal. Kind of a similar idea, more
looking forward. Anybody want to speak
to that one?
I had I had some thoughts. The
the wording in it is that presbyteries
are urged It sounded to me like
presbyteries are urged to have a meeting
sometime in the fall
for that sole purpose.
And I thought maybe the word encouraged
might be
better than urged. Um I doubt my
presbytery would call a meeting
for that. Um maybe
we're unusual, but um
yeah, anyway.
David, did you Were you going to say
something about that?
I did think that the
overture was quite eloquent. And uh I
appreciated that. The thoughtfulness of
the way it was framed and uh
the scripture encouragements um
uh I thought it was a pleasure to read.
Well, and I'd also just well, briefly
just say that I mean, both of these
overtures in their own interesting way,
I think they touch
what our churches typically do or should
be doing and maybe
probably more than any other overture
that's set before us in one sense or
another. Um
there could be arguments that other ones
do as well, but I think both of these in
terms of making disciples and praying
for revival and renewal uh that's
something that all of our churches ought
to be doing and I think it's helpful for
us as an assembly uh to remind ourselves
that we are a court of the church, but
it's a court of the church and that
these things are important and not to
say that everything else we do isn't
important, but these things are part of
what we do together as the bride of
Christ. So, I think they're great.
Yeah, and I don't I don't oppose the
overture.
Uh and I'm assuming there's enough
wiggle room in it. So, if a presbytery
wants to say, "Hey, on September 15th,
let's um
uh
have prayer in our churches or set it
aside as a day that we're all make a
concerted effort to do that rather than
convene a meeting cuz I have to fly to
every presbytery meeting. So.
All right. Well, let's talk about um the
the large category of RAO changes and
we're going to focus on some overtures
dealing with that. And I'm going to
start us out just kind of in order at
first and then we'll jump around a
little bit. But let's start with
overture number five, which is on um
administrative committee members coming
from different presbyteries. It looks
like um there's some debate among this
group about that one. So, I'm going to
let Howie go first and then Steve, if
you want to jump in next and then David,
you can chime in after that. So, Howie,
what do you think about overture five?
Yeah, the the paradigm for us is that
the SJC members have to call come from
different presbyteries
uh
partly because I'm assuming it's a
particularly
uh unique and important um
entity and our presbytery felt that uh
admin committee was as well. There's
admin committee approves the all the
per- permanent committee budgets and
um decides where the GAs are held and
things like that. And um at present,
we've got
of the 11 voting members,
there's two from
one presbytery, two from another, two
from a third. And it just doesn't seem
balanced. So, we thought it'd be best to
just say, "You know, there's 88
presbyteries. We can find 11 guys from
different presbyteries when there's that
many of those." So.
Steve, do you want to chime in on that?
Yeah, very briefly. I mean, I think this
is a uh you know, stop broken really um
and I I think there's a there's a
distinction between overtures and and AC
on one level
or sorry, overtures and SJC
on on that level um
I guess the other thing is I'm not
understand why SJC works the way it
does.
But let's say you had the two best men
who could serve on the SJC and they both
happen to be in the same Presbytery.
And the next guy is 50% of either of
those, but he's in a different
Presbytery. So he gets in. It seems like
an odd way of doing that. And if we
don't have to do that with the AC then
let's let's pick the 11 best men in our
assembly who are willing to serve, which
is another big piece. And if they happen
to be from the same Presbyteries, that's
part of the decision that the assembly
can make. And and have that be a
decision that
the assembly makes rather than you just
can't even decide that you wanted to
have these two men who happen to be from
the same Presbytery on the AC. So that
that that it's a it's a mild no. I'm not
this is not a hill I'll die on or
anything,
but I don't see a real need for it.
Okay. David, what do you think?
Well, um
I'm sympathetic to what Steve was saying
there and and in a sense I
uh
if we're in the abstract, I would run
pure meritocracy. I would want just
every one of the best people doing it.
But the fact of the matter is with a
uh
uh church now spread across a continent
um
the uh
there I think there's a pretty high
premium on making sure
that um there isn't a
Well, in fact, I think people actually
feared this in the north
years and years ago when it seemed like
the whole church was being run in
Atlanta and and then Birmingham and
the um
So, I I do think there's a a really
important
way in which we want to try and get that
meritocracy to work, but be
>> of different presbyteries.
All right. Um unless there's any
thoughts, I'm going to move on to
overture six, which is also Pacific
Northwest and it's about requiring a
minimum number of people to support
something being pulled from omnibus. And
I think there's debate about this.
Howie, I think you might be the lone
voice in support of this. So, why don't
you tell us what you think?
>> the lone of the three, I believe. Yes.
Um
to me, it's frankly ridiculous that one
man out of 2,000
if you have a permanent committee that's
unanimous, a committee of commissioners
that's unanimous, and one guy out of
2,000 could say, "I want that pulled out
of omnibus cuz I want it discussed."
Uh all I'm saying or all our the
overture is saying is, "Let's just bump
that up to Actually, it's 150 It was
revised. 150 guys out of two out of
2,000. If you can get 150 guys, then
it's worth a floor debate. And if that
needs to drop to 100 or 50, something
other than one.
Okay. David, what do you think about
that?
I don't like the omnibus motion at all.
Whenever I have chaired the overtures
committee, I just say I'm not going to
move them in omnibus.
Uh these are things that were all sent
for the assembly to deliberate on.
And uh
we have
um
the really time-consuming parts put into
overtures where there can be give and
take back and forth and changes and so
on.
But I think that
it's not just that one guy
wants to vote.
But if one guy thinks that the church
needs to deliberate more on the matter.
And that seems to me to be a different
thing.
And I'm prepared to say that even that
one guy might look
We had a
a proposal to amend the Book of Church
Order that passed by a large
uh
majority.
It passed the presbyteries by a
And I got up the next year and I was
confident that was mistaken and people
didn't see it.
And so I made a speech
and the assembly overwhelmingly turned
it down.
Um
I I I just think that uh
when we get to the place Well, what I
said the premise of my point is that the
exist part of the existence of what we
are is to be a deliberative body.
And I think that take things up and
gross ought to be uh an irregular part
of our pattern, not a regular part.
Okay, before I give come back to you,
Howie, I want to see if Steve wants to
chime in and then we'll come back to
you.
Yeah, so I I I guess I'm somewhat in
between um I don't have a problem with
ungrossed motions. I hope David isn't
going to propose that the RPR take all
of our recommendations seriatim, one
after the other. Um
but my concern was practically speaking
that means that every person that says
they want to pull something, we have to
stop and take a vote.
Think about, you know, again, there were
25 items that were pulled out of the
omnibus for RPR last year, that means 25
separate clicker votes
that take a long time to do, that might
even take longer than Well, I guess it
ultimately wouldn't take longer than a
vote cuz you have to have a vote anyway.
Um
I was just thinking about the practical
nature of it and that's uh
I
I get the angst, but
practically speaking, I don't think
we're we're not going to save any time
with this. I think we're just going to
add more time to an issue that frankly,
I don't think is a is is a major one.
But I I understand what Howie's trying
to do. I just I don't I don't like this
particular way of doing it. I don't I
don't have a better option other than to
say no.
All right, Howie, what what what do you
want to say? Yeah, the first thing I
want to do is clarify I would be happy
if this is amended to exclude the
overtures recommendations.
As David, I mean that I'm fine with
that. It's but
permanent committee and committee of
commissioners super strong super
majorities and someone gets to pull it
out.
And it's not just the clicker vote on
whether to pull it out or not. It's at
least 10 minutes of debate time on the
matter. So if 25 things get pulled out
by 25 individuals, that's 25 * 10
minutes of debate time on it and that to
me is a waste of the floor's time.
Um but I'm happy to
accommodate David and move in the
overtures committee that we exempt uh
overture committee recommendations from
this. But you know, last year there were
400 RPR recommendations.
I mean, certainly
certainly we need to figure out some way
that one guy can't pull
all 400 of those out of omnibus.
The
The what to do is to pass the
earlier uh motion that it don't come to
the floor at all. Well, I agree with
that. Yes. I agree. That That solve the
problem also.
>> Yeah.
Well, and that would be a great segue in
the next one anyway, but I I I would say
that if RPR changed the way you want it
to, then six I think is not as
important. Okay, well, then let's do
that. Let's Let's go to seven then. And
how you may have to explain this because
it may not be obvious to everyone what
you're doing here.
Well, I don't think it's complicated.
So, I've served on RPR several times.
I've served with Steve happily several
times.
Um
there are so many recommendations
presently just because of our rules that
come out of RPR, and that'll never
change. That's just the way it is.
And there's no reason why the
General Assembly needs to vote on the
first citation of an exception of
substance. If RPR finds something I was
clerk of Pacific Northwest for a while.
If they find something in our minutes,
they just communicate to me and I'll
respond to them. I don't I I would
respond just as quickly as I did with
General Assembly issue in the citation.
You know,
uh
I don't know how many guys show up for
RPR? 80 guys, let's say.
Um maybe less, but
if those guys think that our Presbytery
needs to
clarify something, yeah, we'll do that.
So,
this overture would allow RPR not have
to get a not have to make a
recommendation to General Assembly to
cite the Presbytery to respond the first
time. They do that on their own.
And then when the Presbytery responds,
if RPR doesn't think it's uh
maybe Presbytery misunderstood what they
were asking for or it was
unsatisfactory, RPR can can say, "Please
respond a second time." And then the
only thing RPR needs to take to the
floor is an unsatis- unsatisfactory
second response. They would come to the
GA and say, "We recommend you find that
second response unsatisfactory." Or we
recommend you
punt this to the SJC. So, it doesn't
really give RPR more power per se, and
it doesn't take away power. It just
makes it
a lot more efficient, I think.
Steve, you're the chair of RPR right
now.
I'd love to hear your thoughts on this.
Yeah, so
I I will say first of all, there's
nothing in the overture that I don't
agree with. I mean, and Howie and I have
gone back and forth on some minor edits
and changes over the last couple of
months.
Um I I have I have a couple of concerns,
and and that's really
where I'm at right now. Um in no
particular order,
I do think that there is a sense broadly
in the the denomination
that when RPR, you know, sites a
presbytery on a particular issue, or
recommends it happens, um that that
becomes kind of the uh assembly's view
on that particular issue, which may
change from year to year. And and that,
for lack of a better word, precedence is
part of the
uh the the air that we're breathing
right now in the PCA. And this would
radically change that, I hope, because
if they're just if they're not approved
by the assembly, and they're just the
recommendations of a committee or the
first recommendation,
um
I think there's going to be some mental
switches that have to happen with people
that things are happening drastically
different. That that's a minor issue,
but I think that's that's an issue.
Um I think the other uh concern that I
have is that
um I do think that this will be seen as
giving a lot of power to a committee.
Um
whether or not that's real or whatever,
I mean, I I get Howie's point. I I think
there's an uphill battle that's going to
have to be fought on this. And that
brings me to my only my last issue and
the reason why I said refer back is
because I'm not sure this is a good year
with everything else that we're having
to deal with. And we haven't even talked
about two AIC committee reports that are
coming, plus stated clerk nomination or
election. I mean there's there's some
big things that are coming up.
Um
if if we had only a handful of overtures
really to discuss on the floor at the
end of the week, I'd be happy for this
to be a yes and let's have the
conversation discussion. Um
but I I'm dubious that if we push it
this year, given the volume and the
things that are going on that it'll
actually get passed at the assembly,
much less through the the presbytery. So
that's I'm not opposed to it. It it I'm
just worried about the the logistics of
actually getting it through the assembly
and and in such a way that it gets to
the presbyteries where we can have a
real discussion about it. Well, but it's
an RAO change, so it doesn't have to go
to the presbytery, so. Thank you. That
that's a good point. Thank you. But but
but it's still I mean at at one level
that makes it even more difficult to a
degree because now we're we're
discussing this Tuesday night.
Right. Yeah. Um so that's where I'm but
but I'm
>> how how I was going with that. Yeah,
I've been talking with um
some people of influence
and we might not talk at RAO stuff for
Tuesday night. Um did a little research
the last 7 years
our vote totals have been higher
on the first overture Thursday morning
than they have been on RAO things
Tuesday night.
So it's very possible that the RAOs will
not that the OC will not do a partial
report Tuesday night and it'll be in the
rest just the main overtures committee
reportment. Yeah, we if we pass an RAO
change about the RPR report on Tuesday
night and then the RPR report comes on
Wednesday, that could be interesting
because we just changed the rules.
>> going to take effect. Yeah. [laughter]
Right. Right.
>> It isn't going to take effect.
>> Well, the
the only thing I'd say in response to
Steve, which and I did I do have some
sympathy for
uh
his discussion of sort of the the way in
which we feel about these RPR things and
it's going to have to change
significantly. But the
on the other hand, I feel an urgency to
do it as quickly as possible because I
think
that
last year really things were out of
hand.
And I don't think we can do that year
after year. I don't think people are
reading the report.
Um
I
I just think we are at a almost crisis
point and this would relieve a huge
amount of pressure
on the assembly and I think free up RPR
to do its work better.
Um
so I I feel some urgency to try and see
it through. Although I I I appreciate
what Steve is saying with the
chaos of Last word is that
>> my real hope is just that we're going to
end up with enough time at the overtures
committee Monday and Tuesday to really
dig into this and get really good
consensus from the overtures committee
so that we don't end up with a minority
report or something along those lines,
which I mean that's not the end of the
world, but my point is is that
given the volume of overtures plus the
volume of work at this year's assembly,
that's where I was
maybe this isn't the time, but I'm I'm
I'm happy to do it. We go to do work, so
we might as well do the work.
>> [laughter]
>> All right, one that you guys look like
you're all in favor of was
overture eight from Pacific Northwest
dealing with an earlier deadline for the
floor nominations. Anybody want to speak
to that?
Yeah, we uh we set that up and um it's
just a 24-hour earlier deadline because
um
the
uh
nominated committee meets at 4:30
usually on um
Wednesday,
publishes a supplemental report that
gets uploaded to share file late
Thursday night, and then you've got
floor elections at 9:30 on Thursday
morning. I don't know anybody There
aren't many people that read that. And
um
you know,
if you want to read bio of
John Doe versus Bill Smith,
um there could be a lot of bios to read,
so
um I've talked to the
uh
clerk's office, and uh they're able to
do this.
Um all floor nominations are going to be
electronically filed. They can be filed
uh a month ahead of the General Assembly
as soon as the nominating committee
report gets uploaded to the share file.
So, there's plenty of time to make a
floor nominee. You do it electronically.
And um
just give us an extra 24 hours. It gives
people more time to read the report.
It's an important report. It's an
important report.
Anybody have any other comments on that?
You guys both uh
in agreement there?
Okay. All right. Overture 40 from Sapana
River uh about the terms for stated
clerk and coordinators.
It looks like all of you thought that
was
not a good idea.
So, we don't have to spend a lot of time
on this, but I'd love to give you a
chance to say why it's not a good idea.
Well, I
I I I think that if
uh
i- if the
for if
were to fail,
I would be in favor of 40.
Because it's a little bit of a band-aid.
And at least
gets it so that you're on a year and
there's a break between when you lose
your job and the votes taken and so on.
That would be a minor
remedy. But the major remedy is in 43
and that so I wouldn't vote for it.
>> Yeah. Okay, I should have put those
together. So 43 is proposing um some
terms term lengths for those positions
and you're saying you support that. If
that doesn't pass
Yes, absolutely. And in fact, I think
this is one of the most important uh
in terms of our future leadership. I
think this is one of the most important,
if not the most important overture
before the assembly.
And the reason is
>> It was filed by two very very similar
presbyteries, Pacific Northwest and
Southeast Alabama.
Yeah, so you're being facetious there,
right? So um so the goal is to give the
coordinators
um
and the stated clerk, right? Uh more
time, like job security basically, so
that that incentivizes people that are
good candidates taking the job, being
interested in the job. Yes.
>> I wouldn't say job security as much
because they can be fired anytime during
that four four-year term.
But to attract some I could never
convince my wife to move some place for
a one-year job.
Yeah.
Well, and and my big concern with the
the the year of the Savannah River is
let's say that
contrary to the committee, the general
assembly overwhelmingly thinks that
Howie is doing a horrible job as the
chair of RU F
uh and only one only Howie votes in
favor of himself. Well, now he has 6
months where he's still doing the job.
And everybody thought he was a horrible
at the job, but he gets to do it for
another 6 months.
I I just that that that made no sense to
me. If the whole point is
it makes it easier to remove people
because they don't have to lose their
job on Friday.
Who who would get 6 months of
uh continuation in a job that a a major
group you know the the the assembly
thought they were doing a bad job. So, I
I just I
it seems very very odd to me. And I'm
for the for the reason said, I think 43
and the one from uh Seal uh
that's a that's a good that's a good
change. And I think we ought to do it.
So.
Okay, so 43 yes, all of you guys like
that one. 40 not not as much.
Uh not not a good one. All right, um
let's move on to Ohio 11, overture 11
from Ohio about requiring assessment
data from M&A. That you guys had mixed
responses to this.
Some of it sounded like you guys wanted
to hear more from M&A about whether or
not they want to or they think that's a
good idea. So, David, why don't you
start?
Well, that's where that's where I was.
Um and
um
I have to say that um
the overture itself
I found um
what am I
um
I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I
just leave it. I
I
I think I understand what you're saying.
I think it would be good to hear from
M&A
what kind of data they have, how do they
keep it, and so on.
Um
I'd just say this.
There have been many overtures that have
come before
the assembly
of a
sort of administrative character like
this
that have in the past been clearly
assaults
on the subject that they were
focusing on.
And I don't want to say that's what this
is about, but there have been those that
have been clearly like that.
And so I'd like to hear a full case
before I simply look at the words as
they're written and make a decision.
What about you other guys? Any any
thoughts on that?
Well, yeah, I mean I don't I don't
necessarily think it's a bad idea to
have um
you know, more data reported from
uh any committee per se. Um I I think
David's right. I mean sometimes that
that data is cherry-picked. You know,
let let's
That would be sort of like saying,
"Okay, Steve, you have to upload your
worst sermon from the year so that
everybody at the assembly gets to hear
it."
Um
and
that may not be hard to pick the worst
sermon, but that that doesn't seem like
a
it's really about my health or the
health of my church. It's about trying
to find something that we can point a
stick at and you know, and say, "Look,
this is this is really bad." Uh
I I'm always in favor of more
information as long as it's not, you
know, a data dump, but more information
from our committees about what they're
doing and um and and that sort of thing.
So I mean I don't have a problem with it
conceptually.
Um but I I understand what David is
saying that this does seem potentially,
without uh ascribing motives, uh
potentially to be pointed at um you
know, a weakness rather than
just data generally speaking. So And I
And I would be curious to see what the
committee says. Maybe the committee's
like, "Yeah, this is great. We'd love to
do that. Let Let's We'll tell you
whatever you want to know." Um
but as far as changing
uh requiring it in a RAO, which I'm
assuming that's what that is, um
seems not a great idea to me.
All right. Um one other RAO I wanted to
throw out there to you guys to discuss
was Overture 53 from Great Lakes, which
um would prohibit RPR members from
debating the RPR report. And there was a
there was also mixed um response to this
one among this group. So, Steve, I'm
going to let you start again cuz you're
RPR chair right now. What do you think
>> Sure. about that one? Mr. RPR. Um well,
I I
This it's in my group just to refer back
um because I don't think we're going to
get to it. Um if we did get to it, I
would say no. Um
uh so, there's a whole bunch of reasons.
Um
assuming that the Pacific Northwest on
RPR uh
passes, then I think this is a moot
point anyway. If it doesn't,
um
as Derek, as you know, um that there
have been times in the past where rather
than submitting a minority report, which
requires an hour of the assembly's time,
a member from the committee could go to
a microphone and make a uh
an amendment or propose an amendment.
And if it fails, well, then it or
whether it passes or fails, it takes 10
minutes or whatever it is versus an
hour. Um I would also say that there is
a important difference between overtures
where the members do not get to
participate in debate in RPR. RPR is
100% amendable. And overtures is not at
all. You vote up, down, or refer back.
And so, I get why overtures is that way,
um but RPR, if members of RPR couldn't
speak to the issues, then in one sense,
the men other than the the the chairman
who's speaking from the front, the
people who know the most about the
report
are having to sit on their hands while
everybody else who
maybe didn't even read the report as
David said earlier, they are now getting
to debate and discuss something that
perhaps they know little about. So,
again, I think the Pacific Northwest if
we can get it done, would be the best
solution to all of these problems, but I
I I don't like 53.
Yeah, Howie.
I'm in favor of doing
whatever we can do to prevent minority
reports.
I don't like minority reports
from the SJC, which are theoretically
possible. I don't like minority reports
frankly from overtures that much or from
RPR. So,
um
uh if if Pacific Northwest 7 passes, we
won't need this.
If it doesn't pass,
um
I would probably still vote against this
or refer it back. Um I'd like to see and
I've worked a little bit with Steve on
this. I'd like to see a way to
uh increase the required threshold for a
minority report from RPR and give it
only half as much time as an overtures
committee minority report. Uh you don't
need 90 minutes of floor time
uh or yeah, 90 minutes of floor time for
an RPR minority report on a
first recommended exception of substance
citation. That would be crazy, I think.
So,
Go ahead, David.
Um recall or I hope I'm recalling
correctly,
uh the rule is written just the way
overtures.
And if a person from RPR thinks that
they have something that would
contribute to the assembly's work at
that time, they can ask to be allowed to
speak and the assembly can grant it. And
in fact, when that's happened on
overtures, I've never seen a person
denied.
So, uh I I don't think it would exclude
contributions from people at the floor.
The reason why
uh
I happen to write that rule for
overtures.
And the reason I wrote it is because it
seemed clear to me
that if all the guys who've been arguing
and fighting and sweating over this all
this time now get another shot at the
microphone, they're going to be the
first ones at the mic.
And the assembly who has been excluded
from all of that
that we're never going to chance to
deliberate.
And I think there's somewhat of an
analogy between that and RPR.
Okay. Well, with that, I think we're
going to conclude this uh part of this
discussion. And I want to thank
everybody for listening. We're going to
have uh two more parts to cover um some
of the overtures that deal with titles,
ordination, offices, stop deacon stuff,
miscellaneous, and then we'll have
another video on judicial and uh
administrative overtures. So, hope
you'll come back uh and listen to those.
Thanks for listening.